<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Opinions</title>
    <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Opinions</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ukraine and the future of Nato</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2022-03-10-ukraine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2022-03-10-ukraine/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s day 14 of Putins invasion in Ukraine. More than 2 million Ukrainians have fled the bombardments. Ukrainians are fighting heavily back - delaying the Russians.
Ukraine is asking Nato to establish a &amp;lsquo;No-fly Zone&amp;rsquo; - and enforce it! Nato say&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;No&amp;rsquo;. Ukraine is asking for fighter jets. Poland has offered Soviet-era MIGs - if the alliance takes the responsibility of delivry into Ukraine. (Transfer them to Ramstein and let the US send them to Ukraine).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s day 14 of Putins invasion in Ukraine.
More than 2 million Ukrainians have fled the bombardments.
Ukrainians are fighting heavily back - delaying the Russians.</p>
<p>Ukraine is asking Nato to establish a &lsquo;No-fly Zone&rsquo; - and enforce it!
Nato say&rsquo;s <strong>&lsquo;No&rsquo;</strong>.
Ukraine is asking for fighter jets.
Poland has offered Soviet-era MIGs - if the alliance takes the
responsibility of delivry into Ukraine. (Transfer them to Ramstein
and let the US send them to Ukraine).
The US say&rsquo;s <strong>&lsquo;No&rsquo;</strong>.</p>
<p>In 2008 the with it&rsquo;s in-famous Buchurest-declaration Nato offered
Georgia and Ukraine Nato membership prospects.
Georgian and Ukrainian right-wingers and nationalist put confidence
in these promises and started to feel strong - removing minority
protection regulations for Russians living in their countries.
Russia took action in South-Ossetia in Georgia in 2008 and in Crimea
in Ukraine in 2014.
In neither case Nato or the US were able to counter.
In 2022 with the full Russian occupation of Ukraine going on
Nato and the US once more pull back.</p>
<p>Nato&rsquo;s general secretary Jens Stoltenberg keeps talking:
<em>&lsquo;Every centimeter of Nato soil will be defended&rsquo;</em>
But is this trustworthy?</p>
<p>Some of my Norwegian friends are raising the prospect of Russian
occupation of Norwegian teritory: - Finnmark and The Svalbard Islands -
Russia creating another &lsquo;Buffer Zone&rsquo; towards Nato.
Norwegian forces on their own will not be able to withstand.
Norwegian defense policy is based on one card - Nato coming to the rescue.
A creeping doubt has entered from Ukraine: can we really rely on Nato?</p>
<p><em>Can we still rely on Nato?</em></p>
<p>The US is the core strength of Nato.
When Norway relies on Nato it is basically the US that delivers the guarantee.
In the US priorities are shifting.
Europe is no longer the major strategic interest for the US.
As <a href="https://youtu.be/JrMiSQAGOS4">John Mearsheimer puts it:</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>America&rsquo;s Post-2000 strategic interests are: 1) Western Hemisphere 2) Asia 3) Persian Gulf and 4) Europe.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The US do not want to risk a military confrontation with Russia in Europe -
neither over Geogia, nor over Ukraine, nor over &hellip;&hellip;.</p>
<p>You can fill in what you think.
Will the US confront Russia over Finnmark? Svalbard? Estland? Latvia? Litauen?</p>
<p>The hard fact is that Europe&rsquo;s security arrangement has to be redesigned,
taking into account the new US disinterest as well as the Russian&rsquo;s need
for keeping Nato at a distance.</p>
<p>The Buchurest-declaration was a severe mistake.
Nato is not able to sustain its expansionism -
creating tradegies in Georgia and Ukraine.
Europe can no longer hide under the US umbrella.
Russia is a rising super-power that can no longer be ignored.</p>
<p>If Europe wants to stand up against Putin&rsquo;s atrocities in Ukraine
it will have to do so on her own.
Today Europe is too weak and the US is looking elsewhere -
Putin will have it his way - in Georgia, Crimea, Ukraine, &hellip; &hellip;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Farewell Globalization</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2021-05-30-farewell-globalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2021-05-30-farewell-globalization/</guid>
      <description>To solve the Climate Crisis increasing economic productivity and energy efficiency is not sufficient. Absolute decoupling of economic growth and environmental degradition, including global warming is not feasible (Hickel and Kallis (2019) Is Green Growth Possible?). We will have to stop economic growth itself or even degrow on a global scale.
Growth economists have always had models that in the long run end in a steady state. That&amp;rsquo;s just mathematics. Many economists have been thinking about &amp;lsquo;steady state economics&amp;rsquo; for a long time.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To solve the <em>Climate Crisis</em> increasing economic productivity and energy efficiency
is not sufficient.
Absolute <em>decoupling</em> of economic growth and environmental degradition, including
global warming is not feasible (Hickel and Kallis (2019) Is Green Growth Possible?).
We will have to <strong>stop economic growth itself</strong> or even <strong>degrow</strong>  on a global scale.</p>
<p>Growth economists have always had models that in the long run end in a <em>steady state</em>.
That&rsquo;s just mathematics.
Many economists have been thinking about &lsquo;steady state economics&rsquo; for a long time.
Wikipedia has an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steady-state_economy">overview</a>.</p>
<p>Most recent a new label has been introduced: <a href="https://doughnuteconomics.org/about-doughnut-economics">&lsquo;Doughnut Economy&rsquo;</a>.
The focus is on defining the <em>limits</em> within which the economy can operate without harming
the environment on the one side and providing for a good life for everybody on the other side.
Also focused is the new <em>practises</em> people and businesses can apply in developing
sustainablity principles - moving from &lsquo;exstractive&rsquo; to &lsquo;generative&rsquo; enterprises.</p>
<p>This is the optimistic bottom-up movement of buidling new practises - and is certainly important.</p>
<p>The other side of the coin is more pessimistic:</p>
<p>The world today consists also of the dark side: environmentally
harmfull &lsquo;practises&rsquo; on a large scale that have to be removed, and removed quickly.
These harmful practises contain the &lsquo;normal&rsquo;, &lsquo;business as usual&rsquo; ways of operating
for businesses and working people all over the world.
The really hard task ahead is to knock down these practises.</p>
<p>So, implementing a steady state (or degrowth) economy <strong>now</strong> - due to the
climate urgency ' is quite another issue than small-scale development of &lsquo;doughnut economics&rsquo;.</p>
<p>Herman Daly&rsquo;s famous book “A Steady-State Economy,” includes a 10-point
<em>Transition to a Steady State Economy (SSE)</em>-program.</p>
<p>Point 5 on the list is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Re-regulate international commerce—move away from free trade, free capital mobility and globalization, adopt compensating tariffs to protect efficient national policies of cost internalization from standards-lowering competition from other countries.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just this one point is a very tall order.
Actually, the task ahead is to <strong>undo all achievements of the liberal economic order that
has steered the world in recent decades</strong></p>
<p>How can it be done?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Curse of Development</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2021-05-17-the-curse-of-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2021-05-17-the-curse-of-development/</guid>
      <description>There exists a well-known Swedish song from my childhood. It begins like this:
Lyckliga gatan, du finns inte mere Du er försvinnen med hela kvarteret ...  In English the meaning would be:
Oh Happy Street of my Childhild you no more exits You are now gone together with the whole quarter ...  The lyrics profondly catches the sorry mood of someone experiencing the arrival of the &amp;lsquo;Development Machine&amp;rsquo; in their neigbourhood.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There exists a well-known Swedish song from my childhood.
It begins like this:</p>
<pre><code>Lyckliga gatan, du finns inte mere
Du er försvinnen med hela kvarteret ...  
</code></pre>
<p>In English the meaning would be:</p>
<pre><code>Oh Happy Street of my Childhild you no more exits
You are now gone together with the whole quarter ...
</code></pre>
<p>The lyrics profondly catches the sorry mood of someone experiencing the arrival of
the &lsquo;Development Machine&rsquo; in their neigbourhood.</p>
<p>The time of writing was the 1960s with rapid urbanzation knocking down
happy shanty neigbourhoods bringing &lsquo;modernization&rsquo; - freeways and highrise.</p>
<h1 id="hit-by-development">Hit by Development</h1>
<p>People have been &lsquo;hit by development&rsquo; in this way for as long as capitalism has existed.
It all started with the expulsions from common land  - driving people off their
rural livelihood towards waged labour in the new industrial cities in England a
couple of centuries ago.</p>
<p>And it still goes on &hellip;</p>
<p>While the 1960s had the urbanization craze, the current development craze is &lsquo;Green Growth&rsquo;.
After the &lsquo;economic growth machinery&rsquo; destroyed the atmosphere by CO2-pollution,
global warming has forced governments to require &lsquo;Clean Growth&rsquo; or &lsquo;Green Growth&rsquo; -
still Growth, but no more pouring out climate gases.</p>
<p>At the core is the transition of electricity production from coal/oil/gas to wind/solar and other
renewable sources.
You can burn oil and gas at any time, but the wind and sun are erratic sources.
To ensure continous supply <em>energy storage</em> is required.
For short-duration energy storage batteries are the core option and among
batteries <em>lithium-ion</em> is the dominant technology of today.</p>
<p>Lithium is mostly produced in mines in Australia, Chile and China.
Europe has no lithium production of it&rsquo;s own.
The EU sees that as a strategic deficit - and are eagerly wanting
some supply&rsquo;s of its own.</p>
<h2 id="unhappy-portugal-hit-">Unhappy Portugal hit &hellip;</h2>
<p>Portugal has some lithium ore sites, and a British mining company has
acquired the rights to <em>develop</em> the mine.
But the local farming community don&rsquo;t want <em>development</em> - not even the
promise of 200 new jobs can get them hooked.
As one of the farmers say: <em>We don&rsquo;t want to be excavated and polluted for the
reason of Europeean cities to be cleaner</em>.</p>
<p>The full story <a href="https://www.euronews.com/2021/04/23/portuguese-village-suffers-the-high-cost-of-low-carbon-energy">here</a></p>
<h2 id="unhappy-sierra-leone-hit-">Unhappy Sierra Leone hit &hellip;</h2>
<p>Sierra Leone has beautiful beaches, national parks and thriving local fisheries.
But someone is out to &lsquo;destroy pristine rainforest, plunder fish stocks and pollute fish breeding grounds and several ecosystems&rsquo; - guess who?</p>
<p>DEVELOPMENT! This time disguised by Chinese wanting to build a suitable landing port
for &ldquo;tuna and other bigger fishing” vessels exporting to international markets.</p>
<p>The gold and black sands of Black Johnson beach fringe the African nation’s Western Area Peninsula national park, home to endangered species including the duiker antelope and pangolins. The waters are rich in sardines, barracuda and grouper, caught by local fishermen who produce 70% of the fish for the domestic market.</p>
<p>The $55m  deal struck by the government of Sierra Leone with China to build an industrial fishing harbour on 100 hectares (250 acres) of beach and protected rainforest has been criticised as “a catastrophic human and ecological disaster” by conservationists, landowners and rights groups.</p>
<p>The full store [here](<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2021/may/17/sierra-leone-sells-rainforest-for-chinese-fishmeal-plant">Guardian</a></p>
<h2 id="unhappy-norway-hit-">Unhappy Norway hit &hellip;</h2>
<p>Norway has been a latecomer to wind-power exploitation.
As most of Norway&rsquo;s power production is hydro-based and thus already renewable, there
has simply not been a need for wind, before now &hellip;</p>
<p>New large scale electricity connection cables to neigboring countries (UK, Sweden, Denmark)
has opened up for unlimited electricty production - and someone wants to make profits.
So wind-power has come into the wind - even if Norwegians themselves do not need it.</p>
<p>So international wind capital has arrived also in Norway - whereever the wind blows a
windmill can be put up.
However, resistance is increasing: A survey found that 42 pct of population did not
want onshore windmills, up from 25 pct previous year. 2 of 3 is against windmills in
nature.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/rde/fig/vindkraftmotstand.jpeg" type="" alt=""  /></p>
<p><em>Picture: Mobilization against Wind Mill Development</em></p>
<h1 id="the-devil-in-development">The Devil in Development</h1>
<p>&lsquo;Development&rsquo; has become synonymous with &lsquo;Capitalistic Development&rsquo;.</p>
<p>The economy must grow! We need jobs! We cant live from fish and farming alone!</p>
<p>The argument list is long - so the unhappy people located near any exploitable
resource have no chance of stopping the &lsquo;Development Machine&rsquo;.
Protest, yes - but in the end &lsquo;Development&rsquo; always wins - even if new pollution and
nature destruction is part of play.</p>
<p>The devil in development is capitalism.</p>
<p>Our capability to think beyond capitalism is not great!</p>
<p>The resistance we can see everywhere, however, is a potential.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Case of Norway</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2021-02-26-the-case-of-norway/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2021-02-26-the-case-of-norway/</guid>
      <description>Nordic differences My Swedish friend Torbjörn just sent me a paper clip containing a notice of a Swedish economics professor commenting on the economic situation in Norway. Lars Calmfors in DN 22 feb 2021. The notice is triggered by his involvement in a Norwegian Green Paper Commision on Labour and Income Policy. NOU 2019:7. The Commision shouldpropose new measures to increase labour participation in Norway.
Internationally the Nordic (sometimes only Scandinavian) countries are mostly treated as fairly much of the same under the heading of &amp;lsquo;The Nordic Model&amp;rsquo;.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="nordic-differences">Nordic differences</h2>
<p>My Swedish friend Torbjörn just sent me a paper clip containing a notice of
a Swedish economics professor commenting on the economic situation in Norway.
<a href="https://www.dn.se/ledare/norsk-ekonomi-klarar-inte-bade-minskande-oljeintakter-och-hoga-ohalsotal/">Lars Calmfors in DN  22 feb 2021</a>. The notice is triggered by his involvement in a Norwegian
Green Paper Commision on Labour and Income Policy. <a href="https://www.regjeringen.no/no/dokumenter/nou-2019-7/id2637967/">NOU 2019:7</a>. The Commision shouldpropose new measures to increase labour participation in Norway.</p>
<p>Internationally the Nordic (sometimes only Scandinavian) countries are
mostly treated as fairly much of the same under the heading of &lsquo;The Nordic Model&rsquo;.
This article however points to the particularities of Norway compared to Sweden.</p>
<p>Calmfors&rsquo;s main point is that Norway will not be able to tackle both decreasing oil returns
and high levels of health-related labour market absense when at the same time the population
is quickly aging.</p>
<p>As expected the economists look to &lsquo;increased labour market participation&rsquo; as the
&lsquo;key factor&rsquo; to tackle the problems Norway is now fronting.
(This was in their mandate).</p>
<p>Compared to Sweden the percentage of people living on health-related social contributions are
much higher in Norway (17 pct around the double of Sweden).
Calmfors interprets this figure av &lsquo;medicalization of labour market problems&rsquo; -
which might for sure be true.</p>
<p>When discussing what to do about this situation the differences to Sweden come to the surface.
The Nowegian way is quite more corporativistic than what could happen in Sweden.
After receiving expert proposals from the economists the Commision is enlarged with
participants from Employers and Labour Unions plus from Government.
Together they are charged with finding (for all) acceptable ways forwards.</p>
<p>This way of working together (3-party co-operation) to me lies at the heart of the &lsquo;Nordic Model&rsquo;,
so I am a bit surprised by learning from Calmfors that this is not the way it works in Sweden?
May be the &lsquo;Norwegian Model&rsquo; is not the same as the &lsquo;Nordic Model&rsquo; after all?
Calmfors&rsquo;s conclusion is that this cooperative mode paired with strong egalitarian drives
will create great obstacles for getting more people involved on the labour market.</p>
<p>May be he is right in this. But to me it sounds like an argument to skip the core of
the &lsquo;Norwegian Model&rsquo; - for something more neo-liberalistic?
That would be out of date. The Reagan-Thatcher era is long gone - if not yet
among mainstream economists.</p>
<p>However, to my mind Norway faces problems at the end of the oil age that calls for
looking much more broadly into the strategy of economic transition for the coming decades.
Strikingly the issue of greening the economy is out of focus for this commision.
But let me first take a look at the workings of the &lsquo;Norwegian Model&rsquo; - which has been
in operation from the mid 1930s up till now - and may be longer?</p>
<h2 id="the-norwegian-way">The Norwegian Way</h2>
<p>An interesting analysis of the &lsquo;Scandinavian Model&rsquo; is found in
<a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiIiJOpyIXvAhXQMMAKHW3WDi8QFjAAegQIAxAD&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Flanekenworthy.files.wordpress.com%2F2018%2F01%2Freading-barthetal2014.pdf&amp;usg=AOvVaw0zxuWR3J6zGPD5AMEgo2H6">Barth 2014 (pdf)</a></p>
<p>The conclusion of this work is as follows (my emphasis):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why has the Scandinavian model worked so well? And, why have its
institutions and policies survived, in spite of changing economic and
political circumstances? Our answer to both questions is that there is a
<strong>strong complementarity between the Scandinavian non-market institutions
and capitalist dynamics</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our paper emphasizes the political–economic equilibrium between
three sets of mechanisms. Encompassing organizations in the labor
market follow a policy of wage coordination and wage compression,
with a strong preference for full employment in central bargaining
and microeconomic efficiency in local bargaining. Wage compression
leads to a <strong>higher pace of creative destruction</strong> and further wage compression
with an increasing average wage. More wage equality and higher
average wages fuel the political support for welfare spending. There
might even be a feedback from public welfare policies to productivity
rise and further wage compression. This complementarity explains
why the same outcomes—efficiency and a high level of equality—could
not have been achieved by redistribution through the political system
alone.
This political-economic equilibrium path has benefitted from consistent
policies that have supplemented market forces. Active labor market
programs and moderations on employment protection have been important
policies to facilitate structural change and reallocation of labor
without excessive wage differentials.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A similar concern for consistency is evident from the extensive use of
‘work-fare’ policies, which are used in Denmark, Norway and Sweden to
ensure that work pays in the presence of generous welfare benefits.
High employment reduces the cost of a generous benefit system and increases the tax base.
Active job search or qualification efforts are for example required in order to obtain unemployment benefits.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In sum, the complementarity between the non-market institutions
and capitalist investments help explain why the main institutions and
policies have survived over 80 years. The gains are spread widely across
groups. There are many winners and few losers. Both low paid groups
and employers are clear winners as <strong>wage compression and rising profits
are two sides of the same coin</strong>. High skilled workers are potential losers.
But also high skilled workers may gain from wage moderation, as the
average productivity goes up.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The stability of the Scandinavian model can in part be explained by
the good performance, and the good performance must have been
helped by the stability of the model. The key is that both depend on
the egalitarian aspects of the Scandinavian model that share the gains
of good performance on almost all groups. Since the interactions be-
tween wage coordination, investments, and welfare spending all
strengthen the egalitarian aspects of the model, it would not be possible
to achieve the same egalitarian results by redistribution through the
welfare state only.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So - the &lsquo;Nordic / Scandinavian / Norwegian Model&rsquo; turns out to be just
a smart way to let capitalism evolve.
And it has worked well - on that premise - so far.</p>
<p>The model&rsquo;s &lsquo;golden age&rsquo; was before 1980.
But the neoliberal era - from 1980 onwards has created some dilemmas-
which might be read in the constant decline of the labour parties in
all the Nordic countries during the last couple of decades.</p>
<p>The alliance between Labour and Capital was based on mutual benefits:
Labour Organizations accepted wage restraints as long as capitalist
continued investing in project that created increade number of jobs.
However in the 1980&rsquo;s this closed loop was broken be globalization.
Capitalist&rsquo;s started putting the money into China and other developing
countries instead of investing at home.
Labour is no longer on the winning side of the play.
The gains are no longer as widely spread across groups.
As in other countries there is a rising precariate.</p>
<p>This has been most visible in the other Nordic countries - for Norway
the oil money came in between as a saving angel - allowing for
such &lsquo;economic diseases&rsquo; as 17% health-related social contributions to
people not participating in the labour market.
Thus, the coming end of the oil era put Norway up for greater challenges
than the other Nordic countries, as Calmfors rightly explained.</p>
<p>To green the economy while at the same time get out of &lsquo;oil addiction&rsquo;
is really a double challenge.</p>
<p>To find the way forwards one will need a lot more than main-stream
econmic thinking a la Calmfors.</p>
<p>A starting point could be an &lsquo;evolutionary economics&rsquo; approach.
Interesting extension in the understanding of how the &lsquo;Norwegian Model&rsquo; works
come from <a href="https://evonomics.com/norway-toxic-trickle-down-david-sloan-wilson/">Wlison and Hessen (2015)</a>.
(My emphasis)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The success of the so-called “Nordic Model” is commonly attributed to factors such as income equality, a high level of trust, high willingness to pay tax, which is tightly coupled to strong social security (health, education), a blend of governmental regulations and capitalism, and cultural homogeneity. These and other factors are important, but we think that viewing them through an evolutionary lens is likely to shed light on why they are important. Our hypothesis is that <strong>Norway functions well as a nation because it has successfully managed to scale up the social control mechanisms that operate spontaneously in village-sized groups</strong>. Income equality, trust, and the other factors attributed to Norway’s success emanate from the social control mechanisms.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Time Soon</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2021-01-12-some-time-soon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2021-01-12-some-time-soon/</guid>
      <description>Some Time Soon - things will be the same, but different.
However, we did not notice the emerging change? - or did we?
 David Roberts tweet the day after the Trump-mob storm on Capitol: Feels like we&amp;rsquo;re trapped in a script, a play, that has been performed several times around the world recently. And even though we know exactly how the fall-of-democracy script plays out &amp;ndash; every beat, every chapter &amp;ndash; we&amp;rsquo;re just trapped, helpless, watching it play out</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some Time Soon - things will be the same, but different.</p>
<p>However, we did not notice the emerging change? - or did we?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>David Roberts tweet the day after the Trump-mob storm on Capitol:
Feels like we&rsquo;re trapped in a script, a play,
that has been performed several times around the world recently.
And even though we know exactly how the fall-of-democracy script plays
out &ndash; every beat, every chapter &ndash; we&rsquo;re just trapped, helpless,
watching it play out</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In 2018 Matthew Stewart had an excellent
<a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2018/06/the-birth-of-a-new-american-aristocracy/559130/">piece</a>
in the Atlantic on the morphing of the upper 9.9 percent of American wealth-distribution
into a new <em>Aristocracy</em>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Perhaps the best evidence for the power of an aristocracy is
the degree of resentment it provokes (Matthew Stewart)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Trump is a smart entrepreneur - first in business, then in politics.
Before other he saw the vote potential in the resentment against this new aristocracy -
The Washington Swamp.</p>
<p>Trump succeeded in creating a bizarre aliance between ultra-rich
and the left-behinds of the neoliberal era -
picking up enough votes to start an attack on the ruling aristocracy.</p>
<p>230 years have gone since the French Revolution -
and we still have not seen the return of the pitchforks.</p>
<p>Obama sold &lsquo;change&rsquo; without delivering.
Trump makes &lsquo;change&rsquo;, but only for the benefit of the ultra-rich.
His attacks on the aristocracy in Washington is enough to get him going
with the resentfull.</p>
<p>The aristocracy managed to overturn their 2016-loss with at call
for &lsquo;healing of the nation&rsquo;.
But how should this healing occur?
Only removal of the aristocracy will satisfy the resentfull.
That will not happen witouth the pitchforks.
Some time soon  there is worse to come.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Capitalism</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2020-02-20-beyond-capitalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2020-02-20-beyond-capitalism/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;The Climate Crisis is Capitalism&amp;rsquo;s Waterloo&amp;rdquo; (Yanis Varoufakis)
&amp;ldquo;Black Swan&amp;rdquo; is a label for highly upredictable events with extreme impacts. The concept was made popular by Nassim Nicholas Taleb with his 2007 book of the same title. Some will say the Financial Crisis in 2008 was a black swan. As Queen Elizabeth famously asked the community of Britsish Economists: &amp;ldquo;Why did nobody see this coming?&amp;rdquo; - Although some saw it coming, but not among the mainstream scholars.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>&ldquo;The Climate Crisis is Capitalism&rsquo;s Waterloo&rdquo;</em> (Yanis Varoufakis)</p>
<p>&ldquo;Black Swan&rdquo; is a label for highly upredictable events with extreme impacts.
The concept was made popular by Nassim Nicholas Taleb with his 2007 book of
the same title. Some will say the Financial Crisis in 2008 was a black swan.
As Queen Elizabeth famously asked the community of Britsish Economists:
&ldquo;Why did nobody see this coming?&rdquo; - Although <em>some</em> saw it coming, but not among
the mainstream scholars. Taleb - a former options trader - has later build a
whole theory around the &lsquo;Black Swan&rsquo; - in his five volume Opus Magnus, &lsquo;Incerto&rsquo;.</p>
<p>Now BIS - the Central Bank&rsquo;s &lsquo;Central Bank&rsquo; (Bank of International Settlements in Basel)
has introduced &ldquo;The Green Swan&rdquo; another name for the Climate Crisis as it dawns upon
the community of Central Bankers.</p>
<p>The alarm bells has finally started ringing in the &lsquo;Core of Capitalism&rsquo;.
2019 was the year not only Central Bankers got concerned - even Wall Street is worrying.</p>
<p>The OECD is trying to coordinate the worrying, talking about &lsquo;A New Economic Approach&rsquo;
&lsquo;Beyond Growth&rsquo;.</p>
<p>Only Yanis Varoufakis uses the term &lsquo;Capitalism&rsquo; - and speaks as if some Non-Capitalistic
System really might emerge.
Others stay away from naming &lsquo;The System&rsquo; - and are more concerned about its &lsquo;stability&rsquo; -
focusing on &lsquo;resilience&rsquo; - i.e. how to make Capitalism <em>survive</em> the Climate Crisis.
Naomi Klein&rsquo;s 2014 book &lsquo;This Changes Everything&rsquo; concluded that Capitalism as such
really was what created the Climate Crisis. To get out of the Crisis we would have to
abandon the system itself. But the others have not yet reached such a conclusion.</p>
<p>Some don&rsquo;t like the term &lsquo;Capitalism&rsquo; at all.
John Kay wish we did not use it - thinking it is an obsolete label for today&rsquo;s
economic system.</p>
<p>The ongoing debate is an entertaining exposition of sliding concepts and language -
however, on a very dark and solemn background.</p>
<p>The major divide is between those advocating &lsquo;Green Growth will solve the Problem&rsquo;
and those saying &lsquo;Growth is the Problem, even if it is green&rsquo;. Among the latter
are Jason Hickel and Giorgis Kallis.
This hinges on the very question of whether Capitalism is possible without Growth.
Production for <em>Profit</em> is the core of Capitalism and thus <em>Growth</em>.
&lsquo;Akkumulieren, akkumulieren, dass ist Moses und die Propheten&rsquo; as old Marx put it.</p>
<p>If planetary boundaries forces growth of today&rsquo;s economic system to stop - it
will no longer be Capitalism.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/greta-thunberg-climate-change-future-of-capitalism-by-yanis-varoufakis-2020-01"> * Yanis Varoufakis</a>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Black_Swan:_The_Impact_of_the_Highly_Improbable"> * Wikipedia on Taleb </a>
<a href="https://www.bis.org/publ/othp31.pdf"> * BIS - &ldquo;The Green Swan&rdquo; (pdf) </a>
<a href="https://www.ft.com/content/7bf922ae-4da3-11ea-95a0-43d18ec715f5"> * Wall Street embraces climate action </a>
<a href="https://www.google.com/url?client=internal-element-cse&amp;cx=012432601748511391518:xzeadub0b0a&amp;q=http://www.oecd.org/officialdocuments/publicdisplaydocumentpdf/%3Fcote%3DSG/NAEC(2019)3%26docLanguage%3DEn&amp;sa=U&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjdjt6lid7nAhXL3YUKHZ5sBcgQFjAAegQIARAC&amp;usg=AOvVaw1wHqNvnVHB2QUAm0fryajm"> * OECD - Beyond Growth </a>
<a href="https://naomiklein.org/this-changes-everything/"> * Naomi Klein - This Changes Everything - Capitalism vs The Climate </a>
<a href="https://www.johnkay.com/2018/03/13/moving-beyond-capitalism/"> * John Kay: Moving beyond Capitalism </a>
<a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/13563467.2019.1598964"> * Jason Hickel and Georgis Kallis: Is Green Growth Possible?</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypergranular Macroeconomics</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2019-01-28-hypergranular-macroeconomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2019-01-28-hypergranular-macroeconomics/</guid>
      <description>The Bruegel blog of September 4, 2018 reports from the annual Jackson Hole gathering of central bankers. This year the focus was on implications for central banks of the rise of superstar firms and changing market structure. Of particular interest I found the contribution of Antoinette Schoar (MIT Sloan) - as refered by Bruegel:
Antoinette Schoar looks at the financial market, argues that the rapid growth of new digital technologies has created a market dynamic, where many institutions outside the central bank system might soon have much more comprehensive, more accurate and also more timely information than the regulators.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Bruegel blog of September 4, 2018 reports from the annual Jackson Hole gathering of central
bankers.
This year the focus was on implications for central banks of the rise of superstar firms and
changing market structure.
Of particular interest I found the contribution of Antoinette Schoar (MIT Sloan) -
as refered by Bruegel:</p>
<p><em>Antoinette Schoar looks at the financial market, argues that the rapid growth of new digital technologies has created a market dynamic, where many institutions outside the central bank system might soon have much more comprehensive, more accurate and also more timely information than the regulators. Companies like Google or Amazon can use their data to predict regional sales growth or job losses. Google Trends is just one example of the power of aggregation from individual search information. This poses a challenge going forward that is structural and intellectual. On the one hand we need to think about how central banks can get visibility of the types of data that private-sector institutions are collecting as part of their core business. On the intellectual side the availability of this hyper-granular data asks for a new way of building economic models based on individual purchase or borrowing decisions. This is a challenge to the whole field of (macro)economics.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://bruegel.org/2018/09/monetary-policy-and-superstar-firms/">Bruegel on monetary policy and superstar firms</a></p>
<p><a href="https://bruegel.us1.list-manage.com/track/click?u=b654eefc55844506fec2d988b&amp;id=56b3a386d7&amp;e=cc7b5caad3">Antoinette Schoar (pdf)</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Krugmans Explanations</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2018-01-25-krugmans-explanations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2018-01-25-krugmans-explanations/</guid>
      <description>Mainstream economics failure to &amp;lsquo;see the crisis coming&amp;rsquo; in 2008 is broadly regarded as a deficiency of the theory. However, Paul Krugman now argues that the theory was - and is - &amp;lsquo;good enough for government&amp;rsquo;. The failure of 2008 was not in the theory, but rather in deficient data collection. Macroeconomists &amp;ldquo;overlooked&amp;rdquo; the institutional changes in the financial sector and did not record appropriate data.
The &amp;ldquo;New Keynesians&amp;rdquo; - i.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mainstream economics failure to &lsquo;see the crisis coming&rsquo; in 2008
is broadly regarded as a deficiency of the theory.
However, Paul Krugman now argues that the theory was - and is - &lsquo;good
enough for government&rsquo;. The failure of 2008 was not in the theory,
but rather in deficient <em>data collection</em>. Macroeconomists &ldquo;overlooked&rdquo;
the institutional changes in the financial sector
and did not record appropriate data.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;New Keynesians&rdquo; - i.e. Krugman&rsquo;s &lsquo;Saltwater School&rsquo; based at
MIT and Harvard - took up the challenge by <em>dust[ing] off their old sticky-price models from the 1950s and 1960s, which told them three things:</em></p>
<ol>
<li>Very large budget deficits would not drive up near-zero interest rates.</li>
<li>Even large increases in the monetary base would not lead to high inflation, or even to corresponding increases in broader monetary aggregates.</li>
<li>There would be a positive national income multiplier, almost surely greater than one, from changes in government spending and taxation.</li>
</ol>
<p>Krugman argues that these propositions made the case for budget deficits in the aftermath of the collapse of 2008 which worked “remarkably well.”
This New Keynesian policy was a succes - in contrast to the more inflexible
responses promoted by the &lsquo;Freshwater - Chicago School&rsquo;.</p>
<p>However, fiscal expansion was soon replaced by austerity.</p>
<p>Krugman&rsquo;s version is not taken at face value by Robert Skidelsky who
argues that <em>when Keynes was briefly exhumed for six months in 2008-2009, it was for political, not intellectual, reasons. Because the New Keynesian models did not offer a sufficient basis for maintaining Keynesian policies once the economic emergency had been overcome, they were quickly abandoned.</em></p>
<p><em>The problem for New Keynesian macroeconomists is that they fail to acknowledge radical uncertainty in their models, leaving them without any theory of what to do in good times in order to avoid the bad times. Their focus on nominal wage and price rigidities implies that if these factors were absent, equilibrium would readily be achieved. They regard the financial sector as neutral, not as fundamental.</em></p>
<p><em>Without acknowledgement of uncertainty, saltwater economics is bound to collapse into its freshwater counterpart. New Keynesian “tweaking” will create limited political space for intervention, but not nearly enough to do a proper job. So Krugman’s argument, while provocative, is certainly not conclusive. Macroeconomics still needs to come up with a big new idea.</em></p>
<p><a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/why-no-intellectual-shift-in-economics-by-robert-skidelsky-2018-01">Skidelsky</a></p>
<p><a href="https://academic.oup.com/oxrep/article/34/1-2/156/4781811">Krugman</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Lost Army</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2017-11-16-the-lost-army/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2017-11-16-the-lost-army/</guid>
      <description>The Thai districts on the Myanmar border have very mixed ethnic groups and a rough history:
The Shan are not the only ethnic group living here. Ban Mae Aeb is a small village comprising five ethnic groups living togetger. Besides the Shan, the village is home to Chinese, Lahu, Akha and Lua.
The &amp;ldquo;Lost Army&amp;rdquo; - the republic of China&amp;rsquo;s 93rd Division - fled into Burma after their defeat to the communist.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Thai districts on the Myanmar border have very mixed ethnic groups
and a rough history:</p>
<p>The Shan are not the only ethnic group living here.
Ban Mae Aeb is a small village comprising five ethnic groups living togetger.
Besides the Shan, the village is home to Chinese, Lahu, Akha and Lua.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;Lost Army&rdquo; - the republic of China&rsquo;s 93rd Division - fled into Burma
after their defeat to the communist.
The Chinese Nationalist troop tried to attack Yunnan province in China,
but were pushed into Burma.
Then they were pressured by the Burmese army to move out.</p>
<p>Whereever the Lost Army passed, people from ethnic villages were forced to
join them.
Men were recruited as porters or soldiers while women were cooks and nurses.</p>
<p>The Lost Army swept villages and left no one behind.
The remnants of the Lost Army sought asylum and settled along the
Chiang Rai border, particularily in the mountainous areas.
In exchange for asylum, they fought for Thailand against communists
along the northern border.</p>
<p>Today, descendants of the Lost Army can be found in Doi Mae Salong and
other places along the Chiang Rai border.</p>
<p>Though the villages grew with different ethnic groups, Chinese remains
the village&rsquo;s official language.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.bangkokpost.com/travel/in-thailand/1361415/hilltribe-organics">Thai Hilltribes</a></p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santikhiri">Santikhiri</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/01/15/world/asia/in-remote-thailand-the-lost-soldiers-of-the-kuomintang.html">Kuomintang Villages</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use it or loose it</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2017-06-20-use-it-or-loose-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2017-06-20-use-it-or-loose-it/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I got a reminder from Mars! There is a &amp;lsquo;Starmus&amp;rsquo; conference going on these days, in Trondheim, Norway. One astronaut told about returning to Earth after 43 days in Space - the message being that what you don&amp;rsquo;t use (in Space) you have lost when back (on Earth) - i.e. without gravity your sense of balance get lost - you have to retrain basic mobility capabilities upon return.
So also for elderly people - without exercising mind and body capabilities get lost.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I got a reminder from Mars!
There is a &lsquo;Starmus&rsquo; conference going on these days, in Trondheim, Norway.
One astronaut told about returning to Earth after 43 days in Space - the
message being that what you don&rsquo;t use (in Space) you have lost when back
(on Earth) - i.e. without gravity your sense of balance get lost - you
have to retrain basic mobility capabilities upon return.</p>
<p>So also for elderly people - without exercising mind and body capabilities
get lost. Thats why daily dogwalking keeps me (and the dogs) going.</p>
<p>Beware also the mental vulnurality. Who recalls phone numbers these days?
Say your phone got missed and you need to ask someone else to make a call
for you - would you be able to tell the number to dial?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The times they are a changing</title>
      <link>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2017-05-28-the-times-they-are-a-changing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dyrehaugen.github.io/rde/posts/2017-05-28-the-times-they-are-a-changing/</guid>
      <description>End of an era? Donald Trump has been on his first international trip as President of the U.S. European leaders for the first time in postwar history finds they can no longer trust the U.S. Government. Neither in defence (Nato), climate change (Paris Accord) or trade (TTIP). We are experiencing the slow collapse of the hegemonic US era. Gone are the days of the Washington Concensus and the Neoliberal economic doctrine.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>End of an era? Donald Trump has been on his first international trip as
President of the U.S. European leaders for the first time in postwar history
finds they can no longer trust the U.S. Government. Neither in defence (Nato),
climate change (Paris Accord) or trade (TTIP). We are experiencing the slow
collapse of the hegemonic US era. Gone are the days of the Washington Concensus
and the Neoliberal economic doctrine. The EU establishment seems though to
still cling to these - Merkel &amp; Macron want to pick up the flag abandonned
by the US and to take on a European leadership of prolonged globalisation.
Alas, watershed periods starts with confusion and nostalgia.
Forwards-looking policies are still waiting to emerge.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
