<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Economics on Opinions</title>
    <link>http://localhost/rde/tags/economics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Economics on Opinions</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost/rde/tags/economics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Are human needs infinite?</title>
      <link>http://localhost/rde/posts/2023-03-08-are-human-needs-infinite/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost/rde/posts/2023-03-08-are-human-needs-infinite/</guid>
      <description>Branko Milanovic thinks human needs are infinite and that both Keynes and Marx where wrong to think otherwise.
 Even best among the economists, like Ricardo and Keynes (in “The economic prospects of our grandchildren”) thought that human needs are limited. We should know better today: the needs are unlimited and because we cannot forecast the exact movements in technology, we cannot forecast what particular form such new needs will take.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Branko Milanovic thinks
<a href="https://branko2f7.substack.com/p/robotics-or-fascination-with-anthropomorphism">human needs are infinite</a>
and that both Keynes and Marx where wrong to think otherwise.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Even best among the economists, like Ricardo and Keynes (in “The economic prospects of our grandchildren”) thought that human needs are limited. We should know better today: the needs are unlimited and because we cannot forecast the exact movements in technology, we cannot forecast what particular form such new needs will take. But we know that our needs are not finite.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I beg to differ (see comment on the above link):</p>
<p><em>Human needs are finite - capitalism&rsquo;s needs are infinite. Your argumentation is based on infinite capitalism. Today we should know better.</em></p>
<p>This caused <em>Pechmerle</em> to counter:</p>
<p><em>Human needs are not finite. This is partly a semantic issue - the definition of &ldquo;need.&rdquo; Perhaps if we spoke of &ldquo;wants&rdquo; instead, you would recognize that BM&rsquo;s comment is true.
Ten years ago I couldn&rsquo;t have got - and didn&rsquo;t know it would (or perhaps even then did) exist - classical radio over the internet.
Now that it does, readily, exist I am listening to a classical broadcast from France while typing this comment. I love this capability, and bought a stereo receiver that has the wifi utility built in.
There are many wants like this, and as BM postulates there will surely be many new ones we have not yet foreseen.
In my grandparents generation, radio broadcasts were at first non-existent, and then later something they consumed every single day.</em></p>
<p>My response to this was:</p>
<p><em>Wants are not needs. Wants are socially constructed. Most wants are unneeded.Why else would we &lsquo;need&rsquo; the marketing business?</em></p>
<p>Kevin Kelly adds in an <a href="https://noahpinion.substack.com/p/interview-kevin-kelly-editor-author">interview with Noah Smith</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Our technologies are ultimately not contrary to life, but are in fact an extension of life, enabling it to develop yet more options and possibilities at a faster rate. Increasing options and possibilities is also known as progress, so in the end, what the technium brings us humans is progress.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Technium</em> is Kelly-speak for &lsquo;the interacting web of technologies&rsquo;.</p>
<p>So if technium  is part of life, then &lsquo;human&rsquo; needs will be infinite.
This seems to be the way Branko also is thinking.</p>
<p>But <em>are</em> technologies part of life?</p>
<p>And <em>are</em> progress the same as increasing options?</p>
<p>An isolated theoretical discussion of these isssues may be is a little far-fetched.
What is the <em>relevance</em> of those questions?</p>
<p>Both Marx and Keynes had a vision of <em>sufficiency</em> as the final outcome
of progress.
In the end human needs are finite and we have learned to live a life with
what we have and be happy with that.</p>
<p>This is of course contrary to capitalism&rsquo;s inherent need for accumulation.
History has constructed an economic system based on survival by growth.
If you don&rsquo;t grow your business you will go down.</p>
<p>In the last century, however, an environmental opposision to this worldview
emerged - the <em>sustainability</em> debate.
<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0959652611004987">Sorman and Giampietro (2013)</a> gives this nice summary:</p>
<p>&ldquo;In the 1970s Ehrlich and Holdren proposed the</p>
<p>$$I = P A T$$</p>
<p>relation, where
I - Impact on the environment; P - Population; A - Afﬂuence;
T - Technology.</p>
<p>This relation indicates that the stress on both environment and
natural resources is due to a simultaneous increase of human
population (number of people - an extensive variable) and the
afﬂuence of society (the level of consumption per capita - an
intensive variable). The increase in the
two terms - P and A cannot be compensated by increases in
efﬁciency - T - that is, better technology.</p>
<p>The analysis of Ehrlich and Holdern developed a furious debate,
which, in the 1970s, divided the scientists concerned with
sustainability amid the two sides:</p>
<p>(i) The <em>cornucopians</em> - believers in the perpetual growth. For
those, regardless of whatever increase in P (population size)
and A (afﬂuence); this will always be compensated by an
increase in efﬁciency T (better technology/silver bullets); and</p>
<p>(ii) The <em>prophets of doom</em> - those saying that in a ﬁnite planet
perpetual growth is not possible, no matter what technology
will be invented. For them, all the three terms on the right side
of the equation (PAT) should be changed simultaneously, in an
integrated way, to maintain the activity of humankind within
the carrying capacity of our planet. We can recall here the
famous quote of Kenneth E. Boulding saying that: <em>“Anyone who
believes exponential growth can go on forever in a ﬁnite world is
either a madman or an economist”.</em>&rdquo;</p>
<p>After <em>Limits to Growth</em> in the 1970 the debate went out of steam as
the cornucopians seemed to have won during the neo-liberal era.
Now however the debate is back due to the relentless progress of
climate change - may be there are limits after all?</p>
<p>Of course, the declared <em>techo-optimists</em> are still fighting -
today under the name of <em>Green New Deal</em> or <em>Green Transition</em> -
capitalism is the solution to the problems capitalism has created -
growth can go on - human needs are infinite.</p>
<p>The <em>degrowth</em> camp fights back from the position of sufficiency happiness and
planetary boundaries to capitalisms expansion -
growth has to stop - human needs are finite.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Farewell Globalization</title>
      <link>http://localhost/rde/posts/2021-05-30-farewell-globalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost/rde/posts/2021-05-30-farewell-globalization/</guid>
      <description>To solve the Climate Crisis increasing economic productivity and energy efficiency is not sufficient. Absolute decoupling of economic growth and environmental degradition, including global warming is not feasible (Hickel and Kallis (2019) Is Green Growth Possible?). We will have to stop economic growth itself or even degrow on a global scale.
Growth economists have always had models that in the long run end in a steady state. That&amp;rsquo;s just mathematics. Many economists have been thinking about &amp;lsquo;steady state economics&amp;rsquo; for a long time.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To solve the <em>Climate Crisis</em> increasing economic productivity and energy efficiency
is not sufficient.
Absolute <em>decoupling</em> of economic growth and environmental degradition, including
global warming is not feasible (Hickel and Kallis (2019) Is Green Growth Possible?).
We will have to <strong>stop economic growth itself</strong> or even <strong>degrow</strong>  on a global scale.</p>
<p>Growth economists have always had models that in the long run end in a <em>steady state</em>.
That&rsquo;s just mathematics.
Many economists have been thinking about &lsquo;steady state economics&rsquo; for a long time.
Wikipedia has an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steady-state_economy">overview</a>.</p>
<p>Most recent a new label has been introduced: <a href="https://doughnuteconomics.org/about-doughnut-economics">&lsquo;Doughnut Economy&rsquo;</a>.
The focus is on defining the <em>limits</em> within which the economy can operate without harming
the environment on the one side and providing for a good life for everybody on the other side.
Also focused is the new <em>practises</em> people and businesses can apply in developing
sustainablity principles - moving from &lsquo;exstractive&rsquo; to &lsquo;generative&rsquo; enterprises.</p>
<p>This is the optimistic bottom-up movement of buidling new practises - and is certainly important.</p>
<p>The other side of the coin is more pessimistic:</p>
<p>The world today consists also of the dark side: environmentally
harmfull &lsquo;practises&rsquo; on a large scale that have to be removed, and removed quickly.
These harmful practises contain the &lsquo;normal&rsquo;, &lsquo;business as usual&rsquo; ways of operating
for businesses and working people all over the world.
The really hard task ahead is to knock down these practises.</p>
<p>So, implementing a steady state (or degrowth) economy <strong>now</strong> - due to the
climate urgency ' is quite another issue than small-scale development of &lsquo;doughnut economics&rsquo;.</p>
<p>Herman Daly&rsquo;s famous book “A Steady-State Economy,” includes a 10-point
<em>Transition to a Steady State Economy (SSE)</em>-program.</p>
<p>Point 5 on the list is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Re-regulate international commerce—move away from free trade, free capital mobility and globalization, adopt compensating tariffs to protect efficient national policies of cost internalization from standards-lowering competition from other countries.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just this one point is a very tall order.
Actually, the task ahead is to <strong>undo all achievements of the liberal economic order that
has steered the world in recent decades</strong></p>
<p>How can it be done?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Curse of Development</title>
      <link>http://localhost/rde/posts/2021-05-17-the-curse-of-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost/rde/posts/2021-05-17-the-curse-of-development/</guid>
      <description>There exists a well-known Swedish song from my childhood. It begins like this:
Lyckliga gatan, du finns inte mere Du er försvinnen med hela kvarteret ...  In English the meaning would be:
Oh Happy Street of my Childhild you no more exits You are now gone together with the whole quarter ...  The lyrics profondly catches the sorry mood of someone experiencing the arrival of the &amp;lsquo;Development Machine&amp;rsquo; in their neigbourhood.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There exists a well-known Swedish song from my childhood.
It begins like this:</p>
<pre><code>Lyckliga gatan, du finns inte mere
Du er försvinnen med hela kvarteret ...  
</code></pre>
<p>In English the meaning would be:</p>
<pre><code>Oh Happy Street of my Childhild you no more exits
You are now gone together with the whole quarter ...
</code></pre>
<p>The lyrics profondly catches the sorry mood of someone experiencing the arrival of
the &lsquo;Development Machine&rsquo; in their neigbourhood.</p>
<p>The time of writing was the 1960s with rapid urbanzation knocking down
happy shanty neigbourhoods bringing &lsquo;modernization&rsquo; - freeways and highrise.</p>
<h1 id="hit-by-development">Hit by Development</h1>
<p>People have been &lsquo;hit by development&rsquo; in this way for as long as capitalism has existed.
It all started with the expulsions from common land  - driving people off their
rural livelihood towards waged labour in the new industrial cities in England a
couple of centuries ago.</p>
<p>And it still goes on &hellip;</p>
<p>While the 1960s had the urbanization craze, the current development craze is &lsquo;Green Growth&rsquo;.
After the &lsquo;economic growth machinery&rsquo; destroyed the atmosphere by CO2-pollution,
global warming has forced governments to require &lsquo;Clean Growth&rsquo; or &lsquo;Green Growth&rsquo; -
still Growth, but no more pouring out climate gases.</p>
<p>At the core is the transition of electricity production from coal/oil/gas to wind/solar and other
renewable sources.
You can burn oil and gas at any time, but the wind and sun are erratic sources.
To ensure continous supply <em>energy storage</em> is required.
For short-duration energy storage batteries are the core option and among
batteries <em>lithium-ion</em> is the dominant technology of today.</p>
<p>Lithium is mostly produced in mines in Australia, Chile and China.
Europe has no lithium production of it&rsquo;s own.
The EU sees that as a strategic deficit - and are eagerly wanting
some supply&rsquo;s of its own.</p>
<h2 id="unhappy-portugal-hit-">Unhappy Portugal hit &hellip;</h2>
<p>Portugal has some lithium ore sites, and a British mining company has
acquired the rights to <em>develop</em> the mine.
But the local farming community don&rsquo;t want <em>development</em> - not even the
promise of 200 new jobs can get them hooked.
As one of the farmers say: <em>We don&rsquo;t want to be excavated and polluted for the
reason of Europeean cities to be cleaner</em>.</p>
<p>The full story <a href="https://www.euronews.com/2021/04/23/portuguese-village-suffers-the-high-cost-of-low-carbon-energy">here</a></p>
<h2 id="unhappy-sierra-leone-hit-">Unhappy Sierra Leone hit &hellip;</h2>
<p>Sierra Leone has beautiful beaches, national parks and thriving local fisheries.
But someone is out to &lsquo;destroy pristine rainforest, plunder fish stocks and pollute fish breeding grounds and several ecosystems&rsquo; - guess who?</p>
<p>DEVELOPMENT! This time disguised by Chinese wanting to build a suitable landing port
for &ldquo;tuna and other bigger fishing” vessels exporting to international markets.</p>
<p>The gold and black sands of Black Johnson beach fringe the African nation’s Western Area Peninsula national park, home to endangered species including the duiker antelope and pangolins. The waters are rich in sardines, barracuda and grouper, caught by local fishermen who produce 70% of the fish for the domestic market.</p>
<p>The $55m  deal struck by the government of Sierra Leone with China to build an industrial fishing harbour on 100 hectares (250 acres) of beach and protected rainforest has been criticised as “a catastrophic human and ecological disaster” by conservationists, landowners and rights groups.</p>
<p>The full store [here](<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2021/may/17/sierra-leone-sells-rainforest-for-chinese-fishmeal-plant">Guardian</a></p>
<h2 id="unhappy-norway-hit-">Unhappy Norway hit &hellip;</h2>
<p>Norway has been a latecomer to wind-power exploitation.
As most of Norway&rsquo;s power production is hydro-based and thus already renewable, there
has simply not been a need for wind, before now &hellip;</p>
<p>New large scale electricity connection cables to neigboring countries (UK, Sweden, Denmark)
has opened up for unlimited electricty production - and someone wants to make profits.
So wind-power has come into the wind - even if Norwegians themselves do not need it.</p>
<p>So international wind capital has arrived also in Norway - whereever the wind blows a
windmill can be put up.
However, resistance is increasing: A survey found that 42 pct of population did not
want onshore windmills, up from 25 pct previous year. 2 of 3 is against windmills in
nature.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/rde/fig/vindkraftmotstand.jpeg" type="" alt=""  /></p>
<p><em>Picture: Mobilization against Wind Mill Development</em></p>
<h1 id="the-devil-in-development">The Devil in Development</h1>
<p>&lsquo;Development&rsquo; has become synonymous with &lsquo;Capitalistic Development&rsquo;.</p>
<p>The economy must grow! We need jobs! We cant live from fish and farming alone!</p>
<p>The argument list is long - so the unhappy people located near any exploitable
resource have no chance of stopping the &lsquo;Development Machine&rsquo;.
Protest, yes - but in the end &lsquo;Development&rsquo; always wins - even if new pollution and
nature destruction is part of play.</p>
<p>The devil in development is capitalism.</p>
<p>Our capability to think beyond capitalism is not great!</p>
<p>The resistance we can see everywhere, however, is a potential.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
